Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. John F. Devine Papers, 1952-1974 and undated, bulk 1956-1970 RL.00683
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. John F. Devine papers
1952-1974 and undated, bulk 1956-1970
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00683
22.2 Linear Feet
13,875 Items
Access Restrictions
The Corporate Administration Series and Personnel Series are restricted.
In addition, patrons must sign the Acknowledgement of Legal Responsibility and Privacy Rights form before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. John F. Devine Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1916 Oct. 18 Born, New York, N.Y.
1933 Graduated, Horace Mann School for Boys (Riverdale, N.Y.)
1937 PhB (Bachelor of Philosophy), College of the Holy Cross (Worcester, Mass.)
1940 LLB, Columbia Law School (N.Y.); entered private practice (New York, N.Y.)
1942 Joined U.S. Navy Reserve with rank of Ensign
1946 Discharged from Navy Reserve at rank of Lieutenant Joined J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT) legal department
1953 Review Board Executive at JWT
1953-1959 Chairman, Committee for Radio and Television Administration, American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA)
1954-1961 Vice-President, JWT Radio and Television Department
1960-1963 Consultant to the Committee for Radio and Television Administration, AAAA
1960-1965 General Counsel, JWT
1964 Trustee of JWT Profit-Sharing Trust
1964-1967 Director, National Better Business Bureaus
1965 Vice-President of Administration, JWT
1966 JWT Board of Directors and Executive Committee member
1969 Executive Vice-President of Corporate Administration, JWT
1973 Chairman of JWT-Affiliated Companies
1974 Retired from JWT
1974-1976 Senior consultant to JWT
1983 Oct. 26 Died, Port Chester, N.Y.
Collection Overview
The J. Walter Thompson Company. John F. Devine Papers span the years from 1952 to 1974 but primarily contain files from 1956 to 1970 documenting Devine's activities first as administrator of the Radio/Television Department (1954 to 1960) and then as a corporate executive in the New York office (1960 to 1970). As a whole, the collection provides a glimpse into media advertising operations during the period of transition from radio to television as the dominant medium for product-sponsored advertising and programming. In particular, the papers reveal Devine as an adept financial manager on the corporate level. As Department administrator, Devine was responsible for the development of television programming for specific clients, including Eastman Kodak Company (The Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet, Screen Directors Playhouse, and The Ed Sullivan Show), Ford Motor Company (Ford Theatre, Tennessee Ernie Ford, and Suspicion), Kraft Foods Company (Kraft Television Theatre), and Lever Brothers Company (The Lux Show Starring Rosemary Clooney and Lux Video Theatre), among others. Correspondence, memoranda, and reports indicate the rapid acceptance of television as the primary advertising medium and the concurrent development of specialized departments within JWT to serve the expanding needs of clients. The importance of market research to define product consumption patterns and to refine client advertising promotions is illustrated in research requests, correspondence, memoranda, and reports. The inception and growth of organized labor groups, including the American Federation of Musicians (AFM), American Federation of Radio and Television Artists (AFTRA), American Society of Composers, Authors, and Publishers (ASCAP), Screen Actors Guild (SAG), and Writers Guild of America (WGA), are also delineated in correspondence, memoranda, and reports. In addition to his employment at JWT, Devine was an advertising industry representative to negotiations between television networks and organized labor groups during the period from 1956 to 1960.
After Devine moved to corporate administration in 1961, he dealt with larger corporate issues rather than specific client matters. Administrative files from this period in the collection include documentation of corporate policy, financial charts and projections, client research projects, correspondence and reports from various JWT offices in the United States and Canada addressing a range of issues, such as policies regarding employment of minorities, fiscal accounting, management techniques, and development of new advertising services. There is no material in this collection reflecting Devine's early career in the JWT Legal Department or life after retirement in 1974.
The collection is arranged into three series: the Radio/Television Department Series, the Corporate Administration Series (Restricted), and the Personnel Series (Restricted). Large-format items from the Radio/Television Department Series and the Corporate Administration Series (Restricted) have been relocated to Oversize Materials.
The Radio/Television Department Series includes materials pertaining to department organization and administration; advertising campaigns and television programming sponsored by or produced for specific clients; development of television production facilities; advertising research; and the television networks. Clients with the largest amount of program-specific information include Eastman Kodak Company, Ford Motor Company, Kraft Foods Company, and Lever Brothers Company. Correspondence, memoranda, production reports, and reports relating to specific clients and programming are primarily concentrated in the Client Subseries of the Radio/Television Series, but references to some clients can be found in the Office Files Subseries of the Corporate Administration Series (Restricted).
The Corporate Administration Series (Restricted) contains those office files that generally address broader JWT corporate issues. Devine was particularly involved in efforts to reduce JWT cost expenditures and increase corporate profits, and there are numerous files relating to employee compensation, capital expenditures, financial analysis, and client research projects. The research requests include detailed information about the proposed research, its purpose, methodology, and cost and expense projections. Minority relations, both in employment of minorities by advertising agencies and participation of minorities in television programs and commercials, are also documented in both the Offices and Office Files subseries through a variety of corporate and governmental correspondence, charts, and reports. Devine's records from the Review Board meetings from 1953 to 1955 included in this series are generally not found in other JWT collections. Some of the clients included are Ballantine, National Broadcasting Company, and Radio Corporation of America.
The Personnel Series (Restricted) includes correspondence, memoranda, charts, tables, and notes relating to applicants and current and former JWT employees.
Related materials may be found in other collections within the J. Walter Thompson Archives, including the Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files, the Colin Dawkins Papers, and the Review Board Records.
Advertising agencies -- Management; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Canada; Marketing research -- United States; Labor unions -- Recognition; Television advertising -- United States; Minorities -- Employment -- United States; Television comedies; Television plays, American; Advertising -- United States; Advertising -- History; Advertising -- Research; American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers; American Federation of Television and Radio Artists; American Federation of Musicians; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; Ford Motor Company; Eastman Kodak Company; Devine, John F.; Writers Guild of America; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Kraft Foods Company; Lever Brothers Company; Screen Actors Guild; J. Walter Thompson Company. North America; J. Walter Thompson Company. Radio/Television Dept; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company
- Radio/Television Department Series, 1952-1963 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes advertisement proofs, correspondence, memoranda, rate cards, reports, tables, questionnaires, telexes, telegrams, charts, and verifaxes documenting Devine's activities as administrator of the Radio/Television Department. The rapid growth in the popularity of television in the 1950's and the adjustments made by J. Walter Thompson and other advertising agencies to the new medium are well-documented. Organized into six subseries: Administrative, Client, Programming, Research, Talent Negotiations, and Television Networks. Arranged alphabetically within each subseries.
  - Administrative Subseries, 1955-1960 and undated
    Composed of advertisement proofs, correspondence, memoranda, rate cards, reports, and telexes, telegrams, charts, and verifaxes describing the initial organization and personnel assignments of the Radio/Television Department. In addition, the materials document the rapid development of specialized departments within the company to serve the expanding needs of clients. Arranged alphabetically.
    Other chronological correspondence relating to Devine's corporate administrative duties can be found in the Correspondence Subseries of the Corporate Administrative Series, (Restricted). Some materials moved to Oversize Materials.
    - Department organization, 1955-1960 and undated, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - House advertising on television, 1956-1958 and undated (Box 1)
    - International television advertising, 1956-1958 and undated (Box 1)
    - JWT television firsts, 1959-1958 and undated (Box 1)
    - Legislative issues relating to television advertising, 1958-1960 and undated (Box 1)
    - Media Dept. structure and operation, 1955-1960 and undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1958 and undated (Box 1)
    - New client strategies, 1958 (Box 1)
      Includes memoranda and statistical information relating to tobacco company program sponsorship, and development of concepts for targeting advertising for specific groups.
    - Pay television research, 1958 and undated (Box 1)
  - Client Subseries, 1952-1963 and undated
    Includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, telexes, telegrams, charts, and verifaxes documenting clients and associated programming. The bulk of the materials relate to specific client-sponsored programs and/or commercials, particularly developed for television for Eastman Kodak, Ford Motor Company, Kraft Foods, and Lever Brothers Company, and for radio for P. Ballantine and Sons (New York Yankees and Philadelphia Phillies baseball) and General Cigar, Inc. (New York Yankees baseball).
    Although the contents of the files vary according to year and client, they include advertising and marketing strategies, analysis of the cost of production and profitability of the account to JWT, correspondence relating to legal issues regarding talent and/or union involvement in production, and detailed information about particular programs. Major television shows represented from 1956 to 1958 include: The Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet, Screen Directors Playhouse, The Ed Sullivan Show, Ford Theatre, Tennessee Ernie Ford, Suspicion, Kraft Television Theatre, The Lux Show Starring Rosemary Clooney and Lux Video Theatre. Those files related to Eastman Kodak, Ford Motor Company, Kraft Foods, and Lever Brothers Company also contain daily and weekly production progress reports, detailed budget and cost allocation memoranda, and correspondence relating to various difficulties involved in production of the programs.
    - 1952 (Box 2)
      - P. Ballantine and Sons
        - New York Yankees baseball (Box 2)
    - 1954
      - General Cigar, Inc.
        - New York Yankees baseball (Box 2)
      - P. Ballantine and Sons, 3 folders
        - General, 1954 and undated (Box 2)
        - Foreign Intrigue, 1954 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - New York Yankees baseball, 1954 and undated (Box 2)
    - 1955
      - P. Ballantine and Sons, 5 folders
        - Eddie Cantor Comedy Theatre, 1955 and undated (Box 2)
        - Foreign Intrigue, 1955 and undated (Box 2)
        - General, 1955 and undated (Box 2)
        - New York Yankees baseball, 1954-1955 and undated (Box 2)
        - Philadelphia Phillies baseball, 1954-1955 and undated (Box 2)
    - 1956
      - Aluminum Limited (Box 3)
        - Omnibus, 1956 and undated (Box 3)
      - American Bankers Association (Box 3)
      - Atlantis Sales Corporation (Box 3)
      - Blue Cross Blue Shield (Box 3)
      - Brillo Manufacturing Company
        - It Could Be You, 1956 and undated (Box 3)
      - Buitoni Company (Box 3)
      - Chun King, 1956 and undated (Box 3)
      - Ciba Pharmaceutical Products, Inc.
        - Medical Horizons, 1956 and undated (Box 3)
      - Douglas Aircraft (Box 3)
      - Eastman Kodak, 8 folders
        - Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet, 1956 and undated, 4 folders (Box 3)
        - General, 1956 and undated (Box 3)
        - Screen Directors Playhouse, 1956 and undated, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Union wage increases, 1956 and undated (Box 4)
      - Ford Dealers Advertising Fund, 1956 and undated (Box 4)
      - Ford Motor Company, 11 folders
        - Expenditure recommendations for 1956-1957, 1956 and undated (Box 4)
        - Ford Star Jubilee, 1956 and undated (Box 4)
        - Ford Theatre, 1956 and undated (Box 4)
        - General, 2 folders (Box 4)
        - I Love Lucy (Box 5)
        - Presentation to Ford, May 1956 (Box 5)
        - Programming availabilities and negotiations (Box 5)
        - Television film production reports (Box 5)
        - Tennessee Ernie Ford, 1956 and undated (Box 5)
        - Zane Grey Theatre (Box 5)
    - 1957
      - Ford Motor Company, 7 folders
        - Ford Theatre, 1956-1957 (Box 5)
        - High, Low, 1957 and undated (Box 5)
        - I Love Lucy (Box 5)
        - Project X: The car that went around the world (Box 5)
        - Suspicion, 1957 and undated (Box 5)
        - Tennessee Ernie Ford, 1956-1957 and undated (Box 6)
        - Zane Grey (Box 6)
      - Johns Manville (Box 6)
      - Johnson Motors, a division of Outboard Marine Corporation (Box 6)
      - Joseph Schlitz Brewing Company, 1957 and undated (Box 6)
      - Kraft Foods, a division of National Dairy Products Corporation, 4 folders
        - Budget, 1957 and undated (Box 6)
        - General, 1957 and undated, 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Lever Brothers Company, 10 folders
        - The Eve Arden Show, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - Father Knows Best, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - The Garry Moore Show, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - General, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - Gordon MacRae contract dispute, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - Have Gun, Will Travel, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - The Life of Riley, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - The Lux Show Starring Rosemary Clooney, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - Lux Video Theatre, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
        - On Trial, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Libby McNeill Libby (Box 7)
      - The Mentholatum Company (Box 7)
      - Murine Co., Inc. (Box 7)
      - Northeast Airlines (Box 7)
      - Oneida Ltd. (Box 7)
      - Pan American, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Quaker Oats Company, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Robert A. Johnston Company (Box 7)
      - Scott Paper Company, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Seven-Up Company, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Standard Brands, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Sylvania Electric Products, Inc., 1957 and undated (Box 7)
      - Weco Products Company, 1957 and undated (Box 7)
    - 1958
      - Aluminum Limited Sales, Incorporated, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
      - Atlantis Sales Corporation (Box 8)
      - Boyle Midway-Aero Shave Experimental Film, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
      - Brillo Manufacturing Company, Inc. (Box 8)
      - Chun King Sales, Inc., 1958 and undated (Box 8)
      - Church and Dwight Tic Tac Dough, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
      - Ciba Pharmaceutical Products, Inc. (Box 8)
      - Continental Airlines (Box 8)
      - Eastman Kodak, 8 folders
        - The Adventures of Ozzie and Harriet
          - Daily and weekly production reports, 1958 and undated, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - General, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
        - Beat the Clock (Box 8)
        - Budget, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
        - Commercial work schedule, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
        - General, 1958 and undated (Box 8)
        - The Ed Sullivan Show (Box 8)
      - Elgin (Box 9)
      - Ford Dealers Advertising Fund, 1958 and undated (Box 9)
      - Ford Motor Company, 15 folders
        - Buckskin (Box 9)
        - Destiny (Box 9)
        - Ford Road Show, 1958 and undated (Box 9)
        - General, 1958 and undated (Box 9)
        - High, Low (Box 9)
        - Lucille Ball-Desi Arnaz Show, 1958 and undated (Box 9)
        - Project X: The car that went around the world, 1958 and undated (Box 9)
        - Radio/Television Department call reports, 1958 and undated, 3 folders (Box 9)
        - Suspicion, 1958 and undated (Box 10)
        - Television schedules, 1958 and undated (Box 10)
        - Tennessee Ernie Ford, 1958 and undated (Box 10)
        - Wagon Train, 1958 and undated (Box 10)
        - Zane Grey (Box 10)
      - Johns Manville, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
      - Johnson Motors (Box 10)
      - Kraft Foods, a division of National Dairy Products Corporation, 4 folders
        - General, 1958 and undated (Box 10)
        - Kraft Television Theatre, 1958 and undated, 3 folders (Box 10)
      - Lever Brothers Company, 16 folders
        - The Eve Arden Show (Box 10)
        - Father Knows Best (Box 10)
        - The Gale Storm Show, 1958 and undated (Box 10)
        - The Garry Moore Show, 1957-1958 (Box 10)
        - General, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - Gordon MacRae contract dispute, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - Have Gun, Will Travel, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - House Party (Box 11)
        - Jackie Gleason, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - Keep Talking (Box 11)
        - Lux Playhouse, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - The Lux Show Starring Rosemary Clooney, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - Lux Video Theatre, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - The Price is Right, 1958 and undated (Box 11)
        - Truth or Consequences (Box 11)
        - You Bet Your Life (Box 11)
      - Olympic Committee (Box 11)
      - Scott Paper Company
        - Futures Unlimited (Box 11)
    - 1961
      - Alberto-Culver (Box 11)
      - Allied Van Lines (Box 11)
      - Blue Cross of Southern California (Box 11)
      - Cheseborough-Pond's, 1961 and undated (Box 11)
      - Crocker Anglo Bank (Box 11)
      - Custom Farms (Box 11)
      - Ford Dealers Advertising Associations, 1961-1962 (Box 11)
      - Ford Motor Company, 3 folders
        - General, 1961 and undated (Box 11)
        - J. Walter Thompson Company Study of Ford Motor Company Advertising, 1961-1962 and undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Lever Brothers-Lux television commercial dispute arbitration (Box 12)
      - Northeast Airlines (Box 12)
      - Owens-Illinois Glass Company (Box 12)
      - Radio Corporation of America (RCA) (Box 12)
    - 1962
      - Aluminum Ltd., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
      - American Bankers Association (Box 12)
      - American Petroleum Institute, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
      - Atlantic Sales (Box 12)
      - Beecham Products, Inc., 1962 and undated (Box 12)
      - Blue Cross Blue Shield of New York, 1962-1963 (Box 12)
      - Brillo Manufacturing Company, 1962 and undated (Box 12)
      - Burroughs Corporation, 1962 and undated (Box 12)
      - Chesebrough-Ponds, Inc., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
      - Champion Spark Plug of Canada (Box 12)
      - Chunky Chocolate Corporation, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
      - Congoleum-Nairn, Inc., 1962-1963 (Box 12)
      - Custom Farms, Inc., 1962 and undated (Box 12)
      - Douglas Aircraft Co., Inc. (Box 12)
      - Francis I. duPont and Co., 1962-1963 (Box 12)
      - Eastman Kodak Co., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
      - Ford Dealers Advertising Fund, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
      - Ford Motor Company, 10 folders
        - Copy research (Box 12)
        - Editorial department, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 12)
        - Financial, 1962 and undated (Box 13)
        - "Ford Study"-Marketing Strategies, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 13)
        - General, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 13)
        - Project Monaco ("Project M"), 1962 and undated (Box 13)
        - Radio/Television Production Department, 1962 and undated (Box 13)
        - Research Department, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 13)
        - Television Department, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 13)
        - Traffic Department, 1962 and undated (Box 13)
      - Foundation for Commercial Banks, 1962 and undated (Box 13)
      - Helio Aircraft Corp., 1962 and undated (Box 13)
      - Institute of Life Insurance (Box 13)
      - Irving Trust Co. (Box 13)
      - Kingsberry Homes (Box 13)
      - Kraft Foods, a division of National Dairy Products Corporation, 7 folders
        - Canada (Box 13)
        - General, 1961-1962 and undated (Box 14)
        - Kraft Mystery Theater (Box 14)
        - Perry Como-Kraft Music Hall, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 14)
      - Lever Brothers 1962-1963, 2 folders
        - General, 1962-1963 and undated, 2 folders (Box 14)
        - On-air testing, 1962 and undated (Box 14)
      - Liebmann Breweries, Inc., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 14)
      - Liggett and myers, 2 folders
        - General, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 14)
        - Research authorizations and charges, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 14)
      - Massachusetts Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1962-1963 (Box 15)
      - Mentholatum Company, 1962 and undated (Box 15)
      - National Car Rental Systems, Inc., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - New Holland Machine Company, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - New York World's Fair 1964-1965 Corporation, 1962-1963 (Box 15)
      - Northeast Airlines, Inc., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Pan American Grace Airways (Panagra) (Box 15)
      - Pan American World Airways (Pan Am), 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Phillips Petroleum Company, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Pittsburgh Plate Glass Company, 1962-1963 (Box 15)
      - Planters Peanuts, a division of Standard Brands, 1962-1964 (Box 15)
      - Purolator Products, Inc., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Quaker Oats Company, 2 folders
        - General, 1962 and undated (Box 15)
        - Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-Proposed changes to Dietary Foods regulations, 1962 and undated (Box 15)
      - R. T. French Co., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Radio Corporation of America (RCA), 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Reader's Digest Association, 1961-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - Rowntree Co., Ltd. (Box 15)
      - Scott Paper Company, 1962 and undated (Box 15)
      - Seven-Up Company (Box 15)
      - Standard Brands, Incorporated, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - U. S. Brewers Association, Inc., 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
      - U. S. Lines Company (Box 15)
      - W. F. Young, Inc., 1962 and undated (Box 15)
      - Warner-Lambert, 1962-1963 and undated (Box 15)
    - 1963
      - Alberto-Culver (Box 16)
      - American Electric Power Service Co., 1963 and undated (Box 16)